<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discourse against the outwarde apparell and ministring garmentes of the popishe church</title>
            <author>Crowley, Robert, 1518?-1588.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844763</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844763</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177160</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12285)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177160)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 317:06, 880:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discourse against the outwarde apparell and ministring garmentes of the popishe church</title>
                  <author>Crowley, Robert, 1518?-1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Egidius van der Erve],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1566.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Robert Crowley.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The vnfolding of the Popes attyre.</note>
                  <note>Union Theological Seminary copy identified as STC 6078 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Harvard University. Library and the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 317 (Harvard University. Library) and at reel 880 (Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church vestments --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>price: 3<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A briefe diſcourſe againſt the outwarde apparell and Miniſtring garmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the popiſhe church.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>pſalme. 31.</bibl>
                     <p>I haue hated all thoſe, that holde of ſuperſtitious vanities.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>1566.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:4"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:4"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:5"/>
                  <head>¶ The Booke to the Reader.</head>
                  <l>THe Popes attyre, whereof I talke,</l>
                  <l>I knowe to be but vaine:</l>
                  <l>Wherfore ſome men that wittie are,</l>
                  <l>to reade mee will diſdaine.</l>
                  <l>But I woulde wiſhe that ſuch men ſhoulde</l>
                  <l>with iudgement reade me twiſe:</l>
                  <l>And marke how great an euill it is,</l>
                  <l>Gods Preachers to diſguiſe.</l>
                  <l>I knowe a cocks combe can not take</l>
                  <l>from wiſe men any wit:</l>
                  <l>So doe I knowe that ſuch attyre</l>
                  <l>is for no wiſe man fit.</l>
                  <l>Good mindes can not but much miſlike</l>
                  <l>to ſee good men diſplaſte:</l>
                  <l>But better mindes woulde ſorrowe more,</l>
                  <l>to ſee ſuch men defaſte.</l>
                  <l>Their perſons if ye do reſpect,</l>
                  <l>the matter is but ſmall:</l>
                  <l>But on their office if ye looke,</l>
                  <l>then are they guides of all.</l>
                  <l>The Preacher is a meſſanger,</l>
                  <l>ſent from no worldely wight:</l>
                  <l>But from that Prince that pearleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is,</l>
                  <l>and made all by his might.</l>
                  <l>King Dauid coulde not take it well,</l>
                  <l>but thought himſelfe diſpiſde:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:5"/>
                  <l>When <hi>Hanon</hi> ſent his ſeruauntes backe</l>
                  <l>diſhonorde and diſguiſde.</l>
                  <l>And ſhall not God, thinke you, reuenge</l>
                  <l>himſelfe vpon that route:</l>
                  <l>That to deface or elſe diſplace,</l>
                  <l>his Preachers goe about?</l>
                  <l>Yes doubtleſſe, for the mighty God,</l>
                  <l>will not long tyme endure:</l>
                  <l>The ſpite of ſuch as ſo doe ſeeke,</l>
                  <l>to worke him diſpleaſure.</l>
                  <l>All wiſe men therfore will beware,</l>
                  <l>How they doe ſuch men wrong:</l>
                  <l>As haue ſuch one to take their parte,</l>
                  <l>as for all is to ſtrong.</l>
                  <l>God graunt that all men may once ſee,</l>
                  <l>on which ſide truth doth ſtande:</l>
                  <l>And pray to him for ſuch as be</l>
                  <l>made Rulers of the lande,</l>
                  <l>That they hauing before their eyes</l>
                  <l>the feare of God aboue,</l>
                  <l>May ſeeke to ſet Gods worde in place.</l>
                  <l>and all vayne toyes remoue.</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>A declaration of the doings of thoſe Miniſters of Gods worde and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the Citie of London, which haue refuſed to weare the outwarde apparell, and Miniſtring garmentes of the Popes church.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering how hurteful a thing it is to a chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, to haue the miniſters of Gods worde deſpiſed, and brought into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temt: we haue thought it our dutie, briefly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in writing, &amp; to ſet forth to be ſeene of al men, ſome parte of the reaſons &amp; groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of our doings, in refuſing to weare the outwarde apparel, &amp; miniſtring garments of the popes church.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, we conſider that the power that God hath giuen to his Miniſters, is giuen them that they ſhould therby edifie or build vp the Church of Chriſt, &amp; not deſtroy it, or pul it downe: according as S. Paule writeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinths.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.</note> Of which edifying or buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the church of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ſpeaketh in that Epiſtle that he wrote to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Epheſians. It were to long to cite all his words in order, we will therfore ſet downe certaine ſentences, referringe the Reader to the places, where the ſame are written by S. Paule in that his Epiſtle.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:6"/>
                  <p>Firſt he ſaith thus, <hi>I am non eſtis hoſpites. &amp;c.</hi> Ye are not nowe ſtraungers and forreners, but ye are Citizens togither with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints, and of the houſholde of God, being builded vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> Ieſus Chriſt being the Head ſtone in the corner. In whom whatſoeuer building is encreaſed, it groweth into an holy temple in the Lorde. Theſe wordes doth S. Paule write, to ſignify that the church of Chriſt, which is builded of liuing ſtones &amp; timber, taken out both from among the Iewes and the gentiles, muſt be builded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firme &amp; ſure foundation Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; not vpon any other (for he was that foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the Apoſtles &amp; Prophets builded vpon) and that the building which is ſet vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, doth growe in to an holy Tempell in the Lorde. The builders muſt not ſuffer it to decay, but they muſt ſtill labour diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it may growe into an holy temple, and that till it be as large, &amp; as beautiful, as it is poſſible for it to be in this vale of miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. So farre of woulde S. Paule haue all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> builders of gods temple to be from the pul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling downe, or defacing any parte therof.</p>
                  <p>Againe, the ſame S. Paule ſayth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Epiſtle. <hi>Idem dedit alios quidem Apoſtolos. &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> The ſame hath giuen vs, ſome to be Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſome to be Prophets, ſome to be Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts,
<pb facs="tcp:177160:7"/> ſome to be Shepheardes, and ſome to be teachers, to furniſhe the Saintes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the work af adminiſtration, for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp of the body of Chriſt, till we doe all come into the vnitie of fayth, &amp; the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the ſonne of God. That we may be a perfect man, and come into the meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the ful age of Chriſt. That we be no more babes, to wauer and to be caryed ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out with euery winde of doctrine, through the craftineſſe and wylineſſe of men, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to diſceiue vs. &amp;c. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame chapter, he ſaith: I ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and teſtifie theſe things, euen on the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des behalfe, that ye ſhould not walke as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations doe, in the vanitie of their ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne mindes.</p>
                  <p>By theſe wordes S. Paule doth plainely teache,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e dutie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>er.</note> that al ſuch as are appointed to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in the Church of Chriſt, muſt be ſtill occupied in building, and neuer in pulling down, neither in ſtaying the reaſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> going forwarde with the building they haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne. And that ſuch ſhoulde not be ſo ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhe, that they may be caryed away with euery ſtraunge Doctrine, or deceyued with euery ſubtile perſuaſion, nor walke in the vanitie of their owne mindes, but be ſtayde by the holy worde of God, and in all things acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God, by exerciſing
<pb facs="tcp:177160:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> their Miniſteries according to his inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo nere as poſſibly they may: vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouncing &amp; forſaking all thoſe vnprofitable ceremonies &amp; rytes, that men haue deuiſed without ſure grounde in Gods holy word, in following the vanity of their owne min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. We therefore, knowing that we haue receiued power, to edifie and not to deſtroy, &amp; that a day will come wherin we ſhal be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to receyue at his handes, whoſe builders we are, according to our doings, eyther in building or plucking downe, or in ſtaying &amp; hindring of that which ſhould haue bene builded by others: dare not be ſo bolde as to admit the outwarde &amp; miniſtring appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of the popes church, til it may manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare vnto vs, that the ſame may helpe forwarde, and not pull downe, ſtaye or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the building vp of the Lordes temple, which is his Church or congregation, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed &amp; bought with ſo deare a price, as the heart bloud of his moſt derely beloued, and only begotten Sonne Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>We woulde not therfore in theſe dayes refuſe them, if we might but conceiue an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe, that the vſe of them might helpe forwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes building: but foraſmuch as we ſee playnely the contrary, we may in no caſe admit them.</p>
                  <p>Wee graunt, that of themſelues, they be
<pb facs="tcp:177160:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> things indifferent, and may be vſed or not vſed, as occaſion ſhall ſerue: but when the vſe of them will deſtroy, or not edifie, then ceaſſe they to be ſo indifferent, that in ſuch caſe we may vſe them. For S. Paule hath taught vs, that in the vſe of things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, we muſt alwayes note, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame doe edifie or not. For he hath ſayd, <hi>Omnia ad aedificationem fiant.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. cor. 14</note> Let all things be done to edifie withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If the vſing of the outwarde &amp; miniſtring garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the popes church, cannot now edifie the church of Chriſt, then doe they ceaſſe to be indifferent that we may vſe them. And howe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt is edified by the vſing of theſe thinges, is plaine to as many as will ſee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note>Firſt, the ſimple Chriſtians (ouer whome we ſhoulde haue the chiefe care) are by theſe things ſo grieued, when they ſee vs receiue them, that they ſorrowe &amp; mourne in theyr heartes. And ſuche amongſt them as be not altogether ſo ſtrong, but that they doe yet ſomewhat depende vpon our example and doctrine (as the nature of man is ſo long as he is but a Nouice in Chriſt) thoſe are by vs beaten back to ſuperſtition, from which they were before making haſt to flye. And vnleſſe God doe by his ſpyrite ſtay them: they ſhall by oure example in reuolting to thoſe thinges, which we haue taught to be
<pb facs="tcp:177160:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuperfluous and ſuperſtitious, take occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thinke that ther is no truth in any thing that we haue taught, and ſo cleaue to that falſe religion, wherof theſe indifferent thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges are reliques and remnaunts, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forſake the true Religion of Chriſt, that by oure labour and trauaile began to take roote in them?</p>
                  <p>And when we haue thus ſinned againſt the brethren, and wounded their weake con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences, and ſo ſinned againſt Chriſt: what may wee looke for, but that heauie curſſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> which our Sauiour hath pronounced againſt all ſuche as laye ſtumbling blocks in theyr brothers wayes. It were muche better for vs, that mylſtones were faſtened about our neckes, and we taſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depth of the ſea,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> than that one of theſe litle ones ſhoulde be ſo offended by vs. We dare not therefore admit theſe things, and ſo incurre the daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger of this curſſe. For it is an horrible thing to fall into the handes of the liuing God.<note place="margin">Heb. 10</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondlye, the blinde, ſtubborne, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate papiſtes (whome we ought by all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes poſſible to drawe oute of the darcke dungeon of ignoraunce,<note place="margin">Stubburn Papiſts.</note> ſuperſtition and er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour) ſhal by our receiuyng of theſe things be encouraged, not only to continue in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, ſuperſtition and errour, but alſo to encreaſe in the ſame, being more confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:177160:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> therin by oure retourning agayne to thoſe things, that we haue both by doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and example diſalowed &amp; forſaken: than they coulde haue bene by the perſuaſions of many of their owne opinion. For they muſt needes thinke, that we, which haue ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly refuſed &amp; ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt theſe things, would neuer haue receiued them again, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it had bene made manifeſt vnto vs, that without them our Miniſterie is ſore defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and almoſt vtterly prophaned.</p>
                  <p>The Lord God therfore, when he brought his owne people into the lande of <hi>Canaan:</hi> he commaunded them,<note place="margin">al monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Idolatrie muſt be deſtroied</note> vtterlye to deſtroye all thoſe thinges, that the heathen nations (whom he had caſt out before them) had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed for the furniture of their Idoll ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, leaſt they in vſing of anye of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſhoulde gyue occaſion to the Heathen to thinke, that the God of heauen &amp; earth, had any pleaſure in thoſe thinges,<note place="margin">Deut. 12</note> or neede of the vſe of them in his true ſeruice. Why ſhoulde not wee then feare to giue the lyke occaſion to the papiſtes, to thinke that the true ſeruice of Chriſt can not lacke theyr glittering geare, &amp; that it is more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, when it is furniſhed therwith?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">the biſhops aduertiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note>But this doubt is aunſwered thus, It ſhall be leefull for all miniſters to teache &amp; to proteſt, that they do not vſe theſe things,
<pb facs="tcp:177160:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> as things without the which the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhoulde be prophaned or defaced: but only for decencie and comely order, vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and obedience to our Prince. Yea, and the ſame is playnely ſet forth in the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements, that are publiſhed in print. This doubt therefore is out of doubt.</p>
                  <p>All men ſhal vnderſtand that theſe things be not enforced, as thinges that can not be lacked, but as things decent and comely, &amp; that in the church there maye be an vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in outwarde apparell and miniſterie, &amp; conſequently mutuall loue and vnitie.</p>
                  <p>This wiſedome &amp; pollicie,<note place="margin">Mans polici.</note> paſſeth the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedome of God: And it is muche lyke the wiſedome of them that will haue Images in Churches, not to worſhyp them: but by them to exerciſe theyr ſtrength in refray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worſhipping of them: for (ſay ſuch) to haue Images, and not to worſhip them, is a token of more ſtrength, than it is to refraine from the worſhipping of them, when we haue them not. Euen ſo, to haue and to vſe theſe things, and yet not to haue any ſuperſticion or opinion of holineſſe in them, is much more perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, than to haue no ſuperſtition in them, when they be cleane ſet aſide and left.</p>
                  <p>But the wiſedome of God,<note place="margin">Gods wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſedome.</note> who knoweth what we are, and how ready to abuſe euen
<pb facs="tcp:177160:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> his good creatures which he hath made to ſerue our neceſſitie, &amp; without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe whereof we can not continue in lyfe: hath playnely forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his people the hauing of Images, and hath comaunded them to deſtroy them, &amp; al the furniture of them, as things which he doth deteſt &amp; abhorre.<note place="margin">Deut. 7.</note> And in things not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, and forbidden, he hath ſayde, that his people ſhall not follow their owne fantaſie in adding any thinge to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, but by the mouth of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, he hath vtterly diſalowed their addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſaying:<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Fruſtra me colunt docentes doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, praecepta hominum.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> In vaine doe they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me, which teach doctrines that are but the commaundements of men.</p>
                  <p>The wiſedome of God hath ſayde, Take heede that ye offende not one of theſe little ones that beleue in me.<note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> Wo vnto that man by whom offences come. It were better for that man, that a milſtone were tyed about his necke, and he caſt into the deepe of the ſea, than that he ſhoulde offende one of the leaſt that beleue in me.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe ſhippers, that knoweth wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers doe lye in the ſea, will not of purpoſe ſayle ſo neare thoſe daungers, as he maye poſſibly and eſcape: but contraryewiſe, he will hale aloufe, and be ſure (if the weather will ſuffer him) not to fall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.
<pb facs="tcp:177160:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Yea, &amp; if he ſee, that the weather will not ſuffer him to holde his ſtraight courſe, withour daunger to fal vpon the Rocks or Flattes, he will rather runne vpon an ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther point wher he is ſure to finde ſea rome ynough. And ſhall we that be lodes men the ſhippe of Chriſt (to trye our cunning) creepe ſo neare the flattes or rocks, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we put our whole charge in daunger of periſhing by falling vpon them? God forbydde.</p>
                  <p>That wiſe &amp; politike gouernour of Gods ſhippe S. Paule, woulde not venter ſo far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. But ſeing daunger in the vſe of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thinges he ſayth, <hi>Omnia mihi licent, ſed non omnia conducunt. Omnia mihi licent, ſed non omnia aedificant.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10</note> It is leeful for me a to doe al things (meaning of things indifferent) but all things doe not profit. It is leefull for me to do all things, but al things do not edifie.</p>
                  <p>Againe, he ſayth. <hi>Bonum eſt non manducare carnem, &amp; non bibere vinum, neque quicquam in quo frater tuus impingit, aut offenditur, aut infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ro. 14</note> It is good (ſayth S. Paule) not to eate fleſhe, nor to drink wine, nor to do any other thing, wherat thy brother doth ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or is offended, or made weake.</p>
                  <p>Yea, and the ſame S. Paule, exhorting the Corinthes to ſet them ſelues free from all the ſuperſtitions of the Heathen: ſaith thus vnto them: <hi>Eandem autem habentes remunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem
<pb facs="tcp:177160:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> (tanquam filiis dico) dilatemini &amp; vos.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. cor. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Nolite iugum ducere cum infidelibus.</hi> You alſo hauing the ſame rewarde with me (I ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke as vnto mine owne children) ſet youre ſelues at libertie, be not willing to drawe in one yoke with the infidelles. What confort can there be betwixte righteouſneſſe &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſeneſſe? Or what fellowſhip hath light with darkeneſſe? And what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is there betwene Chriſte and Beliall? Or what parte can a faithfull man haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an infidell? And howe agreeth the temple of God with Images? You are the temple of the lyuing God: as ſayth God, I will dwel in them, &amp; I will walk amongſt them, &amp; I will be their God, and they ſhall be may people. Wherfore, get ye out from amongſt them,<note place="margin">Eſaie. 52</note> and ſeparate your ſelues from them, ſayth the Lorde. And ſee that ye touch no vncleane thyng: and I will receyue you. And I will be your father,<note place="margin">Iere. 32.</note> and you ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters, ſayth the Lorde almightie.</p>
                  <p>Theſe places of ſcriptures doe moue as to flye from al ſuche thinges, as haue bene brought into the church of Chriſt, eyther contrary or beſides the worde of God. And to embrace &amp; vſe thoſe things onely, which are commaunded or haue good grounde in the holy worde of God. Not deſpiſing the
<pb facs="tcp:177160:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> auctoritie that God hath giuen to Princes, and other Potentates: but preferring the commaundement of him that is the giuer of auctoritie, before the comaundement of thoſe that haue none auctoritie of themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, but haue receyued theyr auctoritie at hys hande, and ſhall aunſwere to hym for the vſe therof.</p>
                  <p>And herein we follow the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of God, and the example of all good men. The ſeruaunt of God Moſes, hath ſayde: <hi>Non addetis ad verbum quod ego vobis loquor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 4</note> 
                     <hi>nec auferetis ex eo. Cuſtodite mandata Domini Dei veſtri, quae ego praecipio vobis.</hi> Ye ſhall not adde any thing vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde that I ſpeake vnto you: neyther ſhall ye take any thing from it. Kepe the commaundements of the Lorde your God, which I doe commaunde you. And againe he ſayth, <hi>Non declmabitis, neque ad dexteram, neque ad ſiniſtram:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſed per viam qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praecepit Dominus Deus veſter ambulabitis, vt vi uatis, &amp; bene ſit vobis, &amp; protelentur dies veſtri, in terra poſſeſſionis veſtrae.</hi> You ſhall not bow neyther to the right hande, nor to the left: but by the waye that the Lorde your God hath commaunded you, ſhall ye walke, that ye may lyue and proſper, &amp; that your dayes may be long in the land of your poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Saule</hi> walked not in this waye:<note place="margin">1. Re. 15.</note> but bowed to the right hande of his owne good
<pb facs="tcp:177160:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> intent. And therefore he proſpered not, but was rooted out with al his offſpring, and one ſet vp in his place, that had a pleaſure to walk in that way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">3. Re. 12</note>King <hi>Roboham</hi> walked not in this waye: but bowed to the left hand of his owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious tyrannie: and therefore ten of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue kindreds of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were taken from him, and giuen to his neighbour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">4. Re. 20.</note>King <hi>Ezechias</hi> walked in this way: and therefore in his trouble he founde fauour &amp; helpe at the Lordes hande, and when he was ſicke, he found health, and had .xv. yeares added to his life, &amp; ended his life in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>As many as haue walked in this waye, haue done it, bicauſe they haue had and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hope of a farre better lyfe, and more bleſſed eſtate after this lyfe.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> And therefore, the trouble that they ſuſtayned here, hath not bene greuous vnto them, for they had the rewarde alwayes before their eyes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The true Prophets</note>The true Prophets woulde neuer pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Princes, by addyng to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, nor yet by taking anithing therefor, by bowing to the right hande, or to the lefte: But they dyd alwayes walke ſtraight forth in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s although they did oftentimes ſuſtayne great diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at Princes handes for ſo doing.<note place="margin">falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes.</note> But the falſe Prophets did alwayes marke the
<pb facs="tcp:177160:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> inclinacion of Princes: &amp; faſhion them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of Princes. For they were al brought vp in <hi>Gnatoes</hi> ſchoole, and had learned to ſay, <hi>Aiunt, aio: negant, nego.</hi> If they ſay it, then I ſay it too: If they doe denye it, then doe I denie it alſo.</p>
                  <p>Such were the falſe prophetes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of King <hi>Achab,</hi> who being in number fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hundreth, did with one conſent prophecie that the King ſhould proſper in the warres that he purpoſed to take in hande againſt <hi>Ramoth</hi> in <hi>Galaad.</hi> But the true Prophet <hi>Michea</hi> could not flatter, for he had not bene brought vp in flatterers ſchoole.<note place="margin">3. Re. 22.</note> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaide, <hi>Vidi cunctum Iſrael diſperſum in montibus, ſicut oues non habentes paſtorem. Et ait Dominus, non habent iſti dominum, Reuertatur vnuſquiſque in domum ſuam in pace.</hi> I ſawe all Iſraell ſcattered abrode in the mountaines, as ſheepe without a ſhepheard. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde ſayd, Theſe men haue no maſter, let euery one retourne into his owne houſe in pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. This plaine man that coulde no ſkill of flattering, was ſtriken and caſt into priſon, and threatened a worſe tourne: but the falſe Prophets were highly eſteemed, tyll theyr prophecie was proued falſe, &amp; <hi>Micheas</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie true.</p>
                  <p>It hath alwayes bene the maner of the true prophetes to be ſure that they might truely
<pb facs="tcp:177160:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaye:<note place="margin">Eze. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Haec dicit dominus.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord: but the falſe Prophetes could neuer truely ſay ſo. For they vſed allwayes to prophecie out of their owne fantaſies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 15</note>Our Sauyour Chriſt taught none other thing than the will of his heauenly Father: but the Scribes and Phariſies taught their owne traditions, aduauncing them aboue the commaundements of God.<note place="margin">Mat. 16</note> Wherefore our Sauyour commaundeth his diſciples to beware of their Leuen, that is, of theyr doctrine.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtles were commaunded to go in to all the worlde, and to teache all nations, and to baptiſe them,<note place="margin">Mat. 28</note> &amp;c. And to teache them to obſerue all thoſe things that he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them to obſerue. Which commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they did truely and faithfully exec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. For none of them preached his owne drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,<note place="margin">Mar. 16</note> but euerye one of them preached that which they had learned of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. cor. 11</note>Saint Paule ſaith not, followe mee &amp; doe whatſoeuer I ſhall deuiſe for you to doe, but he ſayth:<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> follow me as I follow Chriſt, and looke on ſuche, as walke as ye haue vs for example.<note place="margin">2. cor. 4</note> And agayne he ſayth: we preache not our ſelues, but Ieſus Chriſt to be the Lorde, and our ſelues your miniſters.</p>
                  <p>We therefore, in refuſing to admit thoſe things which neither haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement
<pb facs="tcp:177160:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> nor grounde in the holy ſcriptures, follow the commaundement of God, and example of al good men, which were builders of the houſe of God before vs.</p>
                  <p>But what is all this to the purpoſe? (ſaye ſome) The things that you refuſe, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iche as God hath neither commaunded nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden: and therfore, Princes haue auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouer them to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde them, eyther to be vſed, or not to be vſed. In refuſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to vſe them at the comaundement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince, ye do not onely reſiſt the ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God your ſelues, but ye doe alſo fall into that inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience, which ye woulde ſo faine ſeeme to be moſte afrayde of. That is, ye be made ſtumbling ſtockes to the ſimple Subiects, who ſeeing your diſobedience, are encouraged to think, that it is none offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce at all to diſobey a Prince. And ſo ſeming to flye from the gulffe, ye are fallen vpon the moſt daungerous Rockes.</p>
                  <p>To this we muſte aunſwere thus: The things that we doe refuſe, are ſuch as God neyther hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded nor forbidden, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than in the vſe and abuſe of them. And therefore, Princes haue no auctoritie either to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde or forbidde them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than ſo. For this is the power, that God hath gyuen to Princes, To ſee his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements executed, to puniſhe ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:177160:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> as breake them, and to defende thoſe that keepe them. Thus doth S. Paule write to the Romanes, Wilt thou be without feare of him that is in auctoritie? Doe wel then, &amp; thou ſhalt not nede to feare him:<note place="margin">Ro. 13.</note> for god hath ordayned him for thy wealth. But yf thou doe euil, then feare: for he beareth not a ſworde for nought. <hi>Nam Dei Miniſter eſt, vltor ad iram, ei qui quod malum eſt fecerit.</hi> For he is gods Miniſter, a reuenger to execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te his wrath vpon that man that dothe the thing that is euill. We muſt therfor be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte, not onely for feare of puniſhement, but euen for very conſcience. But this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection is not to doe at the Princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, whatſoeuer the Prince ſhall for pleaſure commaunde: but humbly to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer at the Princes hande ſuche puniſhemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as the lawes (whereof the Prince hath the execution) doe appoynt vs to ſuffer for the tranſgreſſion therof.</p>
                  <p>And if the Prince ſhall take in hande to commaunde vs to doe anye of thoſe things which God hath not commaunded,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d limits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f true o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>edience.</note> in ſuch ſort that we maye not leaue them vndone, vnleſſe we wil therby ruone into the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the law (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal ſee that in doing therof, we can not edifie but deſtroye) we muſte then refuſe to doe the thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Prince, and humbly ſubmit our
<pb facs="tcp:177160:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſelues to ſuffer the penaltie, but in any caſe not conſent to enfringe the Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, wich is to vſe things indifferent, to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and not to deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>And if the Prince ſhall forbidde any of thoſe things to be done, which in their ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nature be indifferent, ſo that when we ſhall ſee that the leauing of them vndone, ſhall deſtroye or not edifie, then maye not we leaue them vndone, but doe them to the edification of the Church, and ſubmitt our ſelues lowely to ſuffer at the handes of the Prince, the execution of that penalty that the law doth appoint for doing, that thing which the Prince ſhall in ſuche caſe forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to be done.</p>
                  <p>And this is not to giue example of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience (as it is before obiected) but by exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to teache true obedience both to God &amp; alſo to man. Firſt we obey God, in that, both in doing and leauing vndone, we ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the edification of his Church. And then we obey man, in that we doe humblye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues to ſuffer at mans hande, whatſoeuer puniſhments mans lawes doe appoint for our doing or refuſing to doe at mans commaundement.</p>
                  <p>Conſidering therfore, that at this tyme, by the admitting of the outwarde apparel and miniſtring garmentes of the popes church,
<pb facs="tcp:177160:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> not onely the Chriſtian liberty ſhoulde be manifeſtly enfringed, but the whole Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſt alſo, like to be brought to be eſteemed, no other thinge, than the pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Princes: we haue thought it our due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye (being Miniſters of gods worde, and Sacraments) vtterly to refuſe to ſhewe our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmity in receyuing of thoſe things that now are vrged and enforced, and yett wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſubmit our ſelues to ſuffer whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer puniſhment the Lawes doe appoint in this caſe. And ſo to teache by our example, true obedience both to God and man, and yet to keepe the Chriſtian liberty ſounde, and the Chriſtian religion to be ſuch, that no Prince or potentate, may alter or chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the ſame.</p>
                  <p>We hope therefore, that our Prince and all good men, will like well with this our doing, vnderſtanding by Chriſtian libertie, that freedome that Chriſt hath brought vs vnto, by beating downe the particion that was betweene the Iewes and the gentiles, which was the law of ceremonies contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the law written:<note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> In which libertye, S. Paule willed the Galathians to ſtand.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> Not for that the Chriſtian libertye dothe conſiſt onely in this point, but for that this is one of the three points, wherein that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty doth ſtand.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Chriſt hath deliuered vs from the thraldome of ſinne, the curſſe of the lawe, &amp; the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the ſame. By that ſinne, that the firſt man commited, al mankinde became ſo bounde vnto ſinne, that none of Adams na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall poſteritie can be able (without regene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration or new birth) once to deſire to refrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne doing that which is againſt god: From this hath Chriſt deliuered his elected &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen children, ſo that our inwarde man, our ſpirite, our new creature or newe borne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, hath nowe a delight in the lawe of God, as S. Paule writeth to the Romans:<note place="margin">Ro. 7.</note> From that curſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law alſo, he hath ſet vs free. For the ſentence that the law pronounceth againſt al them that breake any point ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is fallen vpon Chriſt, and he is become accurſed for vs all,<note place="margin">Deut. 27.</note> and hathe thereby deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vs from the curſſe. The ceremonies alſo, he hath ended:<note place="margin">Galat. 3.</note> for they ſerued but for the time before his ſuffering of our ſinnes. Being at the point therfore, to gyue vp the ghoſt, he ſayde: <hi>Conſummatum eſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 19</note> It is finiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. The whole deliueraunce of my people is now perfectly wrought. They are deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the tyrannie of ſinne,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> the curſſe &amp; condemnation of the law, and from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude of ceremonies. We are therfore that people that muſt ſerue God in Spirit and truth, and not in figures and ſhadowes.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Leaſt we therefore ſhoulde by admitting theſe things (which were at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt brought into the Churche with opinion of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) bynde our ſelues and our poſteritie to the ſame or lyke neceſſitie, or at leaſt confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that neceſſitie in the myndes of them, which neuer thought them other than ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: we doe vtterly refuſe the admitting of them, chooſing rather, (with cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) to ſuffer the penalties of the law for ſo doing, than by receyuing any of them to fall into that horrible hel of a troubled con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, frome whiche God for his mercye keepe all thoſe that with ſome trouble of conſcience haue not refuſed them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>euerall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oparell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eceſſarie</note>How vnneceſſary a thing it is for the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Gods worde to be knowen from other men, by any outwarde apparell, maye eaſely appeare by that which we reade of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and other Prophetes, of <hi>Peter,</hi> of <hi>Paule,</hi> and other holy men.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Saule</hi> ſought his fathers aſſes, and came where <hi>Samuel</hi> was, and met him: he did not by his apparell knowe him to be a Prophet, but ſayde vnto him, <hi>Indica orô mihi, vbi eſt domus videntis?</hi> I praye thee tell mee, wher is the ſears houſe?<note place="margin">Reg. 9.</note> When the meſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> met with <hi>Eliah:</hi> they dyd not by his apparell knowe that he was a Prophet. But when they had declared to
<pb facs="tcp:177160:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> their maiſter,<note place="margin">4. Re. 1.</note> that it was an hairie man and one that was girded with a leather girdell: the King knewe by thoſe ſignes of auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that it was <hi>Eliah</hi> the <hi>Thesbite:</hi> bycauſe it was not a kinde of apparell, that ſerued for Prophetes to be knowen by, but ſuche homelye apparell as <hi>Eliah</hi> alone vſed to weare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> who was a Prophete, and more than a Prophet, wore not any kinde of garment whereby he might be knowen to be a Prophet:<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> but his appareil was ſuch as was commonly worne in the wilderneſſe or forreſt where his abode was.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peter,</hi> when he followed Chriſt into the highe Prieſtes houſe, was not knowen by his apparell to be one of Chriſtes diſciples, but by his ſpeache. For they that ſtoode by, ſayde not to <hi>Peter:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> thou arte apparelled li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke one of them, but they ſayde, thy ſpeach doth ſhew that thou art of <hi>Galile.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sainct <hi>Hierome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Euſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium,</hi> wherein he doth inſtruct hir, howe to kepe hir virginitie, according as ſhe was purpoſed to doe: doth amongſt other leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons gyue hir thys inſtruction for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of hir apparell. <hi>Veſtis, nec ſatis munda,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hierom ad Euſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chium.</note> 
                     <hi>nec ſordida, &amp; nulla diuerſitate notabilis: ne ad te ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiam praetereuntium, turba conſistat, &amp; digito monſtreris.</hi> Thy garment muſt be neyther
<pb facs="tcp:177160:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> to clenly, nor to ſluttiſhe, neyther notable by anye diuerſytie: leaſt the multitude of them that come againſt thee, and paſſe by, ſhoulde ſtande ſtill, and point at thee with the finger.</p>
                  <p>And the ſame Euſtochium, wryting to Mercella, perſuading hir to leaue the Citie of Rome, and to come and dwell with hir &amp; hir mother Paula at Bethlehem: ſaith thus, <hi>Concurrunt ad haec loca, &amp; diuerſarum nobis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum ſpecimen oſtendunt. Vox quidem diſſona, ſed vna Religio. Tot penè pſallentium Chori quot gentium diuerſitates. Inter haec quae prima in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis virtus eſt, nihil arrogant ſibi de continentiae ſupercilij. Humilitatis inter omnes contentio est: Quicunque nouiſſimus fuerit, hic primus putatur. In veſte, nulla diſcretio, nulla admiratio, vtcunque placuerit incedere, nec detractionis eſt, nec laudis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Men runne togither to this place, and doe ſhewe vs the example of ſundry vertues. The language is dyuers, but the Religion is one. There be almoſt as many quiers of ſingers, as there be diuerſities of nations. And in the middeſt of theſe things, they take vpon them no pride of continencie, which in Chriſtians is the thiefe vertue.</p>
                  <p>The contention that is amongſt them all, is who ſhall be the moſte baſe or humble of them. And whoſoeuer ſhall be in the loweſt rome, the ſame is thought to be the chiefe.
<pb facs="tcp:177160:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> In garments, there is no difference, no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration or ſtraungeneſſe. Howſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe a man to goe in his apparel, it is neyther occaſion to be euil ſpoken of, nor to be prayſed.</p>
                  <p>The whole Cleargie of Rauenna, in the dayes of the Emperour Carolus Caluus, about the yeare of our Lorde <hi>.876.</hi> did wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te an Epiſtle to the Emperour, wherein are theſe wordes. <hi>Diſcernendi à plebe, vel caeteris ſumus, doctrina, non veſte: conuerſatione, non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu: mentis puritate, non vultu. Docendi enim ſunt populi potius quàm ludendi. Nec imponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt eorum oculis, ſed mentibus praecepta ſunt infundenda.</hi> We muſt be diſcerned from the common people, or other men, by doctrine, not by garments: by conuerſation, not by apparell: by puritie of minde, not by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce. For the people muſte rather be taught than mocked. Wee muſte not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue their ſight, but fill their mindes with Preceptes and Rules. This the Cleargie of Rauenna did write, following the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Celeſtinus the firſt Pope of that name. As appeareth in the firſt tome of the Councelles.</p>
                  <p>In the Decrees alſo, the .xxj. cauſe and fourth queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we reade thus. <hi>In priſcis enim temporibus, omnis ſacratus vir, cum mediocri aut vili veſte conuerſabatur. Omne quippè quod non
<pb facs="tcp:177160:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> propter neceſſitatem ſuam, ſed propter venuſtatem ſuſcipitur: elationis habet calumniam. Quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dum Magnus ait Baſilius:</hi> In the olde tymes all ſuch men as were appointed to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, did vſe meane and baſe apparell.</p>
                  <p>For euery thing that is taken for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of it and not for the neceſſitie, bringeth with it the reproche of pride. As ſayth <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Magnus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By theſe places it is manifeſt, that it is nothing neceſſarie, neyther according to the example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt church: that there ſhould be in the outwarde apparell of Miniſters, any ſuch difference, as we are nowe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to admitte.</p>
                  <p>As touching the miniſtering garmentes that are nowe enforced: how vnmeete it is that we ſhould now admit them, ſhall eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare to all that will conſider, whence they firſt came, howe they haue bene vſed, what opinion men haue had, and haue in them, and what ſhall happen vnto vs if we ſhall nowe receyue them.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt, they are partly Iewiſhe, and partly Heatheniſhe.<note place="margin">the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of the Popiſh garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> For the Iewes, bicauſe they were a people muche gyuen to haue a ſenſible gods ſeruice, had many goodly glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering things preſcribed them, to ſtay them from receiuing of thoſe things that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then nations from amongſt whome they
<pb facs="tcp:177160:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> came, and that dwelt rounde aboute them, had and did vſe. But none of thoſe garmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes that <hi>Aarons</hi> prieſtes wore, did lack their liuely ſignifications, to be fulfilled in Chriſt and his church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>When Chriſt therfore was come, and had fulfilled all thoſe things that were by tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe garments figured to be fulfilled by him: then was there no more vſe of thoſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: but it remayned that the people that ſhould ſerue god vnder grace, ſhoulde not ſerue him in figures and ſhadowes.<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> but in ſpirite and truth.</p>
                  <p>Suche partes therefore of the Popes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring garmentes, as haue bene borowed of the Iewes: ought not to be receyued of vs, bicauſe the receyuing of them, ſhoulde argue, that we are not perſuaded that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is yet come, which were as muche as to denye our ſelues to be Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>Some parte of the Popes miniſtring gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments were heatheniſh, as is the Surpleſſe, the Tunicles, the Cheſible and Cope. And ſome mixt of both, as is the Albe, or whyte linnen garment, wherein the Prieſt vſeth to ſay his Maſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>It appeareth by <hi>Gloſſa ordinaria</hi> vpon <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezec. 44.</note> that the Egiptian prieſts vſed a white linnen garment in their ſacrifices. Of what faſhion y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame was, it is not ſhewed there.
<pb facs="tcp:177160:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> The lyke matter writeth S. Hierome vpon the ſame place.</p>
                  <p>The Iewes had alſo <hi>Ephod lineum.</hi> A linnen Ephod or garment, muche like to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Albe. <hi>Platina</hi> in his booke <hi>de vitis Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificum,</hi> wryteth, that Sylueſter the firſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. <hi>320.</hi> yeares after Chriſt, ordeyned that the ſacrament of Chriſtes bodye ſhoulde be miniſtred in a whyte linnen garment one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Rational. deuinoru. <hi>3</hi>
                     </note> bicauſe Chriſtes body was buried in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te linnen cloth.</p>
                  <p>Of this linnen garment <hi>Durandus</hi> in his thirde booke entituled, <hi>Rationale diuinorum,</hi> ſaith, that of neceſſitie it muſt be had in all holy miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. His wordes be theſe: <hi>Veſtis linea, qua quibuſlibet ſeruitiis altaris &amp; ſacrorum vacantes, ſuper veſtes communes vti debent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A linnen garment, which all ſuch as be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to any manner of ſeruices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare and holy things, ought to weare vpon their common garmentes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fications therof.</note>Moreouer, he doth in the ſame place note y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignifications of it. The ſhining witneſſe, ſignifieth, the cleaneſſe or puritye of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The name in latin, which is <hi>Superpelliciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> doth ſignifie the mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our fleſhe, &amp; doth put vs in minde of thoſe garments, that God made for the firſt man and firſt woman, whiche were <hi>Tunicae pelliceae,</hi> Cotes made of pelts. The often vſe of it, doth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb facs="tcp:177160:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> innocentie. The largeneſſe of it, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; the faſhion of it, the paſſion of Chriſt, and the crucifying of Chriſtians, <hi>Vitiis &amp; concupiſcentiis.</hi> To vices and fleſhly luſtes.</p>
                  <p>All this writeth Durandus of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and ſignifications of the Surpleſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe wordes being well wayghed, all men may ſee, that the miniſtring garments of the Popes Church, were taken partely from the Iewes, and partely from the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. And as Polidorus Vigilius,<note place="margin">Cap. 5.</note> dothe note in his fourthe booke, <hi>De inuentoribus rerum,</hi> they came from the Egyptians by the Hebrues.</p>
                  <p>How theſe garments haue bene abuſed,<note place="margin">Idolater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iurers &amp; ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the Popiſh garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te</note> is manifeſt to as many as haue conſidered the doings of Idolaters, ſorcerers, &amp; coniurers. For all theſe doe nothinge without them. The Idolater dare not appeare before his Idoll to offer any ſacrifice, vnleſſe he be in his ſacrificing garmentes. For without his preſcript garments, he is not only without hope to purchaſe anything for others by his ſacrifice: but alſo in great feare to ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne great diſpleaſure him ſelfe at the hands of his god, whoſe wrath he is perſuaded, that he hath deſerued by enterpriſing to do ſacrifice, lacking ſuch miniſtring garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes as are of neceſſitye required therein. And hereof it commeth, that no maſſyng Prieſt
<pb facs="tcp:177160:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> will take vpon him to ſay Maſſe, if he lacke any one thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the order of his Maſſe is appointed to be had, his Albe, his Stoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, his Fannel, his Amias, his Cheſible, his Cup, his Corporaſſe cloth, his Altare or <hi>Superaltare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if any of al theſe thinges be lacking, or not halowed by the Biſhop or Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane: then can he ſay no Maſſe, yea if his Cuppe or Corporaſſe cloth hath bene tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by any ſeculer perſon, it will not ſerue his turne, till it be new halowed. Thus ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Maſſing prieſt with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idolaters, &amp; is him ſelfe the greateſt Idolater of all.</p>
                  <p>The Sorcerers and Coniurers alſo, can neyther haue the inſtruments y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they work with, nor vſe them, when they haue them: but they muſte haue ſome helpe of ſome of theſe thinges. Their <hi>Aarons</hi> Rodde, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they worke wonders, can not be had without much helpe of theſe things. Their <hi>Aqua luſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> their coniured water (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no Circle can be made to keepe out the diuel) can in no wiſe be made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Surpleſſe or Albe. The diuels can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be called vp, nor bounde, when they be called vp, nor yet coniured downe agayne, without an halowed Stoale.</p>
                  <p>If there were no more in vs therefore, but a deſire, not to ſeeme to be Idolatours,
<pb facs="tcp:177160:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſorcerers or coniurers, it were ynough to moue vs to refuſe to admit the Miniſtring garmentes of the popes church. but there is more to moue vs. For we ſee what opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion men haue had, and haue ſtill in them: and what ſhall happen vnto vs, if we ſhall nowe receyue them.</p>
                  <p>The blinde and obſtinate papiſts ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that three ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue of theſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> that without theſe things no holineſſe can be in ought that we do: and therefore they wil not be partakers with vs in any thing.</p>
                  <p>The weake papiſtes, which are contented to be partakers with vs, doe fynde none ſo great faulte with vs, as for that we Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter without their Miniſtring garmentes, and ſtartche breade<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſimple goſpellers doe ſuppoſe, that foraſmuch as the Papiſtes doe holde that without theſe things there can be no right miniſtration: they ought not to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with thoſe that vſe them.</p>
                  <p>And we our ſelues (although we know the indifferencie of them in their owne nature) yet when we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how theſe three ſortes, doe eſteeme them, cannot be perſuaded that we ſhould ſhew our ſelues meete to occupie the place of Paſtours or ſhepheards in the church of Chriſt, if we ſhould now vſe them.</p>
                  <p>A learned Father, &amp; one whoſe bones we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re burned after his death, for the doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:177160:21"/> that he preached in his lyfe,<note place="margin">Martinus Bucerus</note> &amp; lefte behinde him in wrytinge, beinge required to wryte his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t what he thought meete to be done in this caſe: aunſwered that he coulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to ſuffer ſome great payne in his owne body, vpon condition y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe things were vtterly taken away. And in ſuch caſe as we are nowe, he willeth, that in no caſe they ſhould be receyued: as doth moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly appeare in that which he wrote vpon the xviij. chapter of S. Mathewes goſpel, and vpon theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Bucers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſuche as maintain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popiſhe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> 
                     <hi>Vae mundo ab offendiculis.</hi> Woo to the worlde by the reaſon of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or occaſions of fallings: wherafter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye wordes to this effecte, he ſayth: That no man will earneſtlye ſtryue to maintayne theſe ſuperſtitious ceremonies, but ſuch as be eyther open enimies to Chriſt, or elſe bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſlyders from Chriſt. <hi>Hoſtes aut deſertores.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And bicauſe it is ſayde of ſome men, that this Father is agaynſt vs in this matter: we ſet downe his wordes written from Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mebridge, to a moſt deare friende of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the ſeas, cited by Theodore Beze in his aunſwere to the calumniatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Baldwine, which wordes were written the .xij. of Ianuarie in the yeare of our Lord <hi>1550.</hi> The wordes are theſe: <hi>Quòd me mones de puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate rituum, ſcito, hîc neminem extraneum
<pb facs="tcp:177160:21"/> de his rebus rogari. Tamen ex nobis, vbi poſſumus, officio noſtro non deſumus, ſcriptis, &amp; coram. Ac in primis, vt plebibus Chriſti de veris paſtoribus conſulatur. Deinde etiam, de puritate puriſsima, &amp; doctrinae &amp; rituum.</hi> Where as ye write vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puritye of Ceremonies, ye ſhall vnderſtande, that no ſtraunger is here called to councell in thoſe matters.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding, when occaſion doth ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs, we are not ſlack in doing our dutie, both by writing and worde. And eſpecially, that the people of Chriſt maye be prouided of true Shepherds, and then alſo, that both doctrine and ceremonies, maye be brought to moſt perfect puritie. And in the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle he ſayth: <hi>Sunt qui humaniſsima ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp; euaneſcentibus cogitationibus, velint fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento Antichriſti conglutinare Deum &amp; Belial.</hi> There be ſome which by moſt wordly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; vaine deuiſes, would with the leuen of Antichriſt glewe togither God &amp; Belial. Here is the iudgement of Bucer, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge the retayning of Ceremonies, plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelye ſet forth, ſpeaking expreſſelye of this Churche of Englande.</p>
                  <p>And Peter Martyr, whoſe iudgement hath in this matter bene oftentimes aſked, dothe more than once in his writinges call them <hi>Reliquias Amorraeorum,</hi> leauings or rem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunts of the Amorites.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Martyr.</note>And although he do in ſome caſe thinke that they maye be borne with for a ſeaſon: yet in our caſe, he would not haue them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to remaine in the church of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Doctor Ridley late Byſhop of London, when one Doctor Broches with others at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xforde came to degrade him a little befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re his death, perſuaded the ſayde D. Ridley to put on the Surpleſſe with the reaſt of the Maſſing garmentes, which he vtt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to doe. Sayinge (as in the hiſtorie of Martyrs appereth,) truely if it come on me (meaning the Surpleſſe) it ſhall be againſt my will. Then the ſayde D. Brockes cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſayde Surpleſſe with the reſt of the trinkets appertayning to the Maſſe, to be by force put vpon him. Wherevpon he dyd vehemently inuey againſt the biſhop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,<note place="margin">Ridl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> callinge him Antichriſt, and all that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell foliſh and abhominable, yea, to fonde f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ice in a play. Wherwith Doctor Broc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes beinge very angrie, bad him holde his peace, for he did but rayle. Hereby it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth what eſtimation that worthy Martyr of God had of the Popiſhe garmentes at the tyme of his death. Albeit in the dayes of King Edwarde, he did ſtoutely maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gainſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uell.</note>Biſhop <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uell</hi> in his replye to <hi>D. Harding</hi> in the <hi>.442.</hi> page againſt the breaking of the
<pb facs="tcp:177160:22"/> Sacrament, hath theſe wordes: <hi>Verilye in the houſe of God, that thing is hurtfull, that doth no good. All the Ceremonies of the Church ought to be cleare and liuelye, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to edifie.</hi> Yf theſe thinges now in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie can be proued ſuch, then will we not refuſe them. But in caſe they want all theſe properties (as vndoubtedly they doe) then by this mans iudgement we may well reiect them.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall happen to vs, yf we ſhall now receyue them, ſhall be plaine ynough to them, that will but waighe theſe fewe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes afore written? It ſhall happen vnto vs, as it ſhould haue happened vnto Moſes if he would haue conſented to bring the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues back againe into Egipt, after he had brought them out of that lande, &amp; through the read Sea.</p>
                  <p>We haue by doctrine brought many out of the Romiſhe ſlauerie of Idol ſeruice, and nowe by example we haue begonne to go before them, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter aboliſhing of all tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe chaines of darkeneſſe, wherewith they, and we haue bene long tyme holden in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable captiuitye: and were it meete, that we ſhoulde now a freſhe binde our ſelues &amp; them with the ſame chaines?</p>
                  <p>Whileſt wee oure ſelues were in thoſe chaines, although we did knowe them to be
<pb facs="tcp:177160:23"/> bondes: yet we were for a ſeaſon content to beare them, tyll we might be able to cauſe others to ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which we our ſelues did ſee. And now that we haue by the helpe of god cauſed ſome men to ſee what theſe thinges are, and haue in theyr ſight ſhaked them of from our owne neckes, and looſed the ſame from their neckes alſo: what ſhould our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing of them againe be other than a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backe againe into Egipt, and a leading thither agayne, of all ſuche as we haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to bring thence?</p>
                  <p>We haue taught that which <hi>Tertul.</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: <hi>Nihil dandum Idolo, ſic nec ſumendum ab Idolo. Si in Idolio recumbere alienu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt à fide, quid in Idoli habitu videri?</hi> We may giue nothing to the Idoll,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ilitis.</note> ſo may we take nothing of the Idoll. If it be a thing againſt the fayth to ſitte at meate in the Idolles feaſt, what is it to be ſeene in the habite of an Idolater?</p>
                  <p>We haue taught that the popiſhe maſſe is Idolatrie, that all the popes holy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as his waxe, his aſhes, his palme, his fyre, his holywater, &amp; other his holy things made holy by his coniurations, are deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Chriſtes glory, &amp; therefore to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed of all Chriſtians: and ſhall it not be as meete for vs now to flye in lyke maner from the vſe of thoſe garments that they taught
<pb facs="tcp:177160:23"/> to be ſo neceſſarie in their coniurations?</p>
                  <p>Surely we can not be perſuaded, but it is as great an euill for vs, now to weare in our Miniſtration anye of thoſe coniuring garments, as it is for any of them that doe knowe what theſe coniured things are, to be partakers of them.</p>
                  <p>Leſt we ſhoulde therfore encourage the obſtinate and blinde Papiſtes to ſticke ſtill in their popiſhe puddle:<note place="margin">the cauſes that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>achers of the goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to refuſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes.</note> leſt we ſhould beat back thoſe that are by oure cryinge vnto them begynning to craule out of that pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle: leſt we ſhould ſhake off and hurle he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adlong into that puddle, thoſe that are by our meanes plucked out therof, and yet not ſo freed from the filth therof, but that they haue neede to be made cleane by our helpe, &amp; ſtayed from ſlyding in againe: yea and leſt we ſhoulde make ſorowfull and pyerce the heartes of them, that be quite eſcaped, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhoulde ſee vs by whoſe meanes they haue eſcaped, bewadled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame filth our ſelues: and ſo bring al that we haue taught into doubt, and all that we ſhall teache in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuſpicion, we haue thought it meete for vs, vtterly to refuſe all theſe thinges that now are vrged.</p>
                  <p>For if we, that haue by doctrine proued theſe things to be ſuperfluous, &amp; in the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of them ſuperſtitions, ſhall nowe receyue
<pb facs="tcp:177160:24"/> them our ſelues, and ſo in doing (although not in words) affirme them to be neceſſary? What obſtinate Papiſt will not be the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re confirmed in the reuerende opinion of them? what yong nouice in Chriſt, will not afreſhe embrace them? what weakling will not againe inclyne to them: And what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Chriſtian will not weepe in hys heart to ſee them?</p>
                  <p>And ſhall not the bloude of all theſe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at our hands: ſhal not we once hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re that horrible ſaying that Chriſt ſhal once pronounce againſt ſuche as we ſhould here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhewe oure ſelues to be: <hi>Tollite ſeruum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam. &amp;c.</hi> Take vp that naughty ſlaue, bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hym hande and foote, and caſt hym into vtter darkeneſſe: there ſhal be weeping and wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
                  <p>Fearing therefore to loſe our ſelues with the loſſe of ſo many ſoules, beſides our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues: we haue choſen rather to venture the loſſe of worldely commoditie, than to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarde that which no earthlye treaſure can bye. Truſting that our Prince and all other in auctoritie will fauour our iuſt cauſe, and not miſlike with vs, bycauſe we feare god more than man, and are more loth to loſe the heauenly Kingdome, than earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</p>
                  <p>We hope that all wiſe men doe ſee, what
<pb facs="tcp:177160:24"/> marke the earneſt ſoliciters of this matter do ſhoot at. They are not, neyther were at anye tyme Proteſtantes: but when tyme woulde ſerue them, they were bloudy perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters, &amp; ſynce tyme fayled them, they haue borne back as much as lay in them. Shall we think then, that ſuch do ſeeke the aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cement of gods glorye, in the ſetting forth of his true religion? no, no. Theyr purpoſe is, in vs (ſielly wretches) to deface the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus, whiche thing they ſhall neuer be able to bring to paſſe.</p>
                  <p>For thoughe we, lyke cowardes, ſhoulde runne from our Captayne, and yelde our weapons into the handes of oure enimyes: yea thoughe we ſhoulde (lyke traitours) tourne our pikes againſt him yet wil he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the victorie. For he hath the heartes of his enimies in his hande, &amp; can cauſe them to take his part, and to vſe vs as traytours ſhoulde be vſed.</p>
                  <p>Our goodes, our bodyes, and our lyues, we do with al humble ſubmiſſion yelde into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of gods officers vpon earth: but our conſcience we keepe vnſpotted in the ſight of him that ſhall iudge al men. Deſiring no thing, but that it may be free for vs by doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to teach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flocke of Chriſt, whereof we haue taken charge: and when we haue ſo taught them, to goe before them, in doing
<pb facs="tcp:177160:25"/> that which we haue taught according to the truth of gods holy worde. That when we ſhall appeare before that great ſhephearde Chriſt, our flocke with vs, and we with our flock may heare theſe ioyful words, <hi>Euge ſer ue bone &amp; fidelis, &amp;c.</hi> Well done thou good &amp; faythfull ſeruaunt: bicauſe thou haſte bene faithful in the thing that is of ſmall value, I will make thee Ruler ouer muche: enter thou into thy Lordes ioy. Whiche ioy ſhall vndoubtedly be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to as many as vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly ſhall loue the comming of that ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard. To whome, with the eternall father and the holy ghoſt, be all honor, glory and dominion for euer. </p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Eccleſiaſticus. 4.</bibl>
                        <p>Stryue for the truthe euen vnto death, and the Lorde God ſhall fight for thee.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>¶ A godly prayer, agreable to the tyme and occaſion.</head>
                  <p>O Almighty God, great Iudge of all, Father of mercy, and louing Lorde of thy flock and congregation: we doe acknowledge they goodneſſe, thorowe which thou haſt vouchedſafe to chooſe and call vs into the ſocietie of thy Saintes, the fellowſhip of thyne elect, the folde of thy ſheepe, wherein allwayes thou haſte dealt
<pb facs="tcp:177160:25"/> with vs in all thinges, as with thine owne inheritance, thy choſen ſheepe, and beloued Lambes. For this thy great kindeneſſe, we doe yelde to thee our moſte humble &amp; hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thankes. We doe confeſſe alſo, that on our behalfe, for want of due conſyderation of this thy goodneſſe, &amp; our dutie, we haue grieuouſly offended thee, not onely in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull vſinge thy benefites, but alſo in wilfull and ſinfull abuſing thy mercie.</p>
                  <p>To holy aſſemblies we haue ioyned oure ſelues in the exerciſes of thy worde and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, of prayer, &amp; charity, yet not with ſuch zeale &amp; diligence as we ought, but with that lothſomeneſſe &amp; contempte, whiche we ought not. In comming to them dayly, we haue filled our fanſie, rather than feede our faith, we haue come to them more of cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me than of conſcience, we haue heard much more with oure eares, than we digeſted in our mindes. And thus with harde hearts, hearing much, doing little, promiſing faire, performing nothinge in effect, we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned vncorrected, not amended, to the great offence of thy diuine maieſtye.</p>
                  <p>Of thy diſpleaſure kindled heretofore againſt vs, we haue bene diuers wayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed. For euen as thou dideſt leaue a remnaunt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Cananites,</hi> not caſt out from amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thy people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to be ſnares, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,
<pb facs="tcp:177160:26"/> and thornes in their ſydes and eyes, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not fully cleane vnto thee: ſo doe the remnants of the Remiſhe ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtill amongeſt vs, to witneſſe thy wrath againſt our colde loue of ſincere ſeruing thee, &amp; yet is not our zeale inflamed to better. The ſharp ſcourges which we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſeene &amp; felte, together with ſtraunge ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhewed in heauen &amp; earth, haue teſtifyed thyne anger agaynſt vs, but we earth and aſhes, are not yet by them taught our good.</p>
                  <p>The miniſters of thy worde, ſeing oure ſinful ſtate, haue ſeuerely threatned greater plagues to fal on vs, but we haue tryfled of our tyme, &amp; not heartly tourned vnto thee. And therfor it is, that euen now we ſee (as a begynning of greater vengeaunce) their heartes (whoſe power ſhoulde procure the correction of our miſchiefe) not only holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in neglect &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of that they ſhould do, but bent alſo to maintayne that they ſhould deſtroy, to the hindering of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of thy goſpel, which they ſhould ſet forwarde.</p>
                  <p>Are not the reliques of Romiſhe Idolatrie ſtoutely retayned? Are we not bereaued of ſome of our paſtors, who by worde &amp; exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſought to free thy flocke from thoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences? Ah good Lord, theſe are now by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer put downe from paſtural cure, they are forbyd to feede vs, theyr voyce we can not
<pb facs="tcp:177160:26"/> heare. This is oure great diſcomfort. This is the ioy &amp; triumph of Antichriſt his lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, our enimyes: yea, &amp; that is more heauy, increaſe of this miſery, is of ſome threatned of the wicked hoped for, and of vs feared, as thy iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt vs for our ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>And nowe Lorde, what can we ſay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of faces is ours. We haue ſynned &amp; done amiſſe, we confeſſe our fault. As iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is thyne iuſtelie to correct, ſoe mercye is thyne alſo to pardon and to helpe the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. We perſuaded of thy goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs in Ieſus Chriſt, doe knowe, that of loue thou doſt nowe chaſtyſe vs as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Correct vs O Lorde, but not in thy wrath. Remember thy louing kindneſſe, and in the ryches of thy great mercye, pardon &amp; forgiue all oure ſynnes, through which, we haue thus offended thee. O Lord blot them out of thy remembraunce, by the bloude of thy ſonne Ieſus. And let thy good ſpiryte now tranſforme vs from our olde euils, ſo that we commit them no more, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther apea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no cauſe to moue the memorie of them anye more in thy holy ſight: but rule vs to growe in regeneration, that this our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lyfe maye bring forth plentifully thoſe fruites of the ſpirite, which do pleaſe thee. O heauenlye Father, ſtay thy ſtroke nowe begon. Reſtore our helpes to vs agayn. Yea
<pb facs="tcp:177160:27"/> of thy liberall goodnes, giue more of ſuche ayde and help, as thou knoweſt nedefull to worke the thorow reformation of oure ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te generally, and of eche one of vs particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlye.</p>
                  <p>Much good haſt thou wrought vnto vs by our ſouerayne, and the miniſters whom thou haſt appointed to gouernement. Doe not withdrawe thy graces frome them for oure ſinnes ſake, but rather increaſe thy good gyftes in them, for thy mercye ſake. Indue them with increaſe of knowledge, zeale, and diligence, that they may doe that which is to be done, to gyue thy glorious goſpell the full courſe, ſo that by it perfyte ſtabliſhment maye be wrought of thy reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in ſincerity, and of ciuile regiment, in peace and equitie.</p>
                  <p>Loke Lord and Iudge moſt iuſte on the proude bragge and boaſt of antichriſt thyne enimy, cut his courage, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founde his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, diſapoint his hope, breake his power, &amp; giue him that vtter ouerthrow, that there do not remayne ſo muche as a memorie or token of him, to be had in regarde, but that his memorye maye be had in confuſion. O Lorde ſet vp thy glorye, remoue thy wrath, reſtore thy mercye, comforte thyne afflicted, tourne thy louing countenance to vs, poure
<pb facs="tcp:177160:27"/> forth thy grace on vs, build vs vp in Chriſt, &amp; loue vs ſtill. Let the trumpet of thy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell with ſuche power &amp; plenty be blowne, that all fleſh may hearken &amp; yelde thereto, thyne elect to their comforte, the reprobate to their confuſion. And let this blaſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue without ceaſſing with due effect, vntill that laſt trump be ſounded by thine Archa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, at the daye of Chriſt, And come Lorde Ieſus. In thy name, O Chriſt our Capitay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, we aſke theſe things, &amp; praye vnto thee o Heauenlye father, ſaying. <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi> O Lord increaſe our faith whereof we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke confeſſion. <hi>I beleue in God, &amp;c.</hi> Ariſe O Lord, and let thyne enimyes be confounded. Let them vnderſtand that againſt thee they fight. Let them flye from thy preſence, that hate thy godly name. Let the grones of thy afflicted, enter in before thee. And for thy name ſake waſh away all dregs of Poperie and ſuperſtition that preſentlye trouble the ſtate of thy church. And preſerue the Vyne whiche thy ryghthande hathe planted, that the glory of thyne annointed Ieſus Chriſt oure Lorde, maye clearely ſhyne here and before all nations. </p>
                  <closer>So be it.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>To my louynge brethren that is troublyd abowt the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe aparrell, two ſhort and comfortable Epiſtels.</p>
                  <p>Be ye conſtant: for the Lorde ſhall fyght for yow, yowrs in Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>¶ To all my faithful brethren in Chriſt Ieſu and to all other that labour to weade out the wedes of popery, Peace in the Lorde Ieſu be with you, and make you perfite in all good workes to doe his will, working in you that which is pleaſant in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>DEare Brethren,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>becauſe we are crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid for gods glory the edification one of another in Chriſt, and are bounde to ſerue thervnto by wealthe or woo, lyfe or death, and cheifly, they to whom God haue geuen the greter gyftes, and whom he hath callyd to higher romes, are moſte bounde to be zelous for gods glory with godly zelouſie to profyt the churche and ſponſe of Chriſte vnder their charge, and that by no ſubteltye as the Apoſtel warnithe, they ſhulde be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted from the ſymplicitie of Chriſt: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no doubt of your good zealle and diligence. My good fathers &amp; deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who at firſt callid to the battel, to ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue for gods glory and the edification of his people, againſt the Romiſh reliques and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Antichriſt, I doubt not but that you wyl coragiouſlye and conſtantlye in Chriſt, rape at theſe rages of Gods enemyes, and that you will by this occaſion race vp many as grete enormites that we all know, &amp; labo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re to race out all the dregges &amp; remnants of
<pb facs="tcp:177160:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> tranſformid popery, that are crept into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, by to much lenite of them that wylbe namid the Lordes of the cleargie: what is he that hath the zeale of gods glory before his face, that wyl not ioyne both in prayer, and in ſufferinge with you, in ſo good a cauſe, that is ſo much for gods glory, and the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacion of gods church, in the pure ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite of Chriſtes word &amp; ſacramentes, wherin our enemies and perſecutours are ſtrangely bewitchid. I wote not by what Circes cupe, that they do make ſuche a diuerſite betwixt Chriſtes worde &amp; his ſacramentes, that they can not thinke the worde of God ſafelye y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe preachid, &amp; honorably inough hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd, without cap, cope, ſurplis. But that the ſacraments the maryinge, the buryinge, the churching of wemen, &amp; other church ſeruice, as they call it, muſte nedes be decored with croſſinge, with capping, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſurpleſſing, with knelinge, with preti wafer cakes, and other knackes of poperi. O Paule that thou were a lyue, thou durſt tell thoſe politike gentel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that ther hath bin to much laboure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoued vpon them in vaine, thou durſte ſay vnto them, as thou dideſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians, that they eat not the Lordes ſupper, but pley a pagent of their owne to blynde the people, and kepe them ſtill in ſuperſticion, fare from the ſymplicite of Chriſtes ſupper: but howe
<pb facs="tcp:177160:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> many ſely ſowles is ther that dothe beleue veryly, that they haue an Engliſh maſſe, and ſo put no difference betwene truth &amp; falſhod, betwene Chriſt and antichriſt, betwene God and the deuell, they are ſtrangely bewitched. I ſay that thus wyll bynde theyr Englyſhe preſthode &amp; ſacraments, but muche more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntid that can fynd no garments to plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe them. But ſuch as haue ben polutid open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with popiſhe ſuperſticion &amp; Idolatry, but moſt of all in this point ſhall theyr madnes apere to all poſterites, that they make theſe Antichriſtian rages <hi>Cauſam ſine qua non,</hi> that is, a cauſe without which ther is no holy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery in Chriſt, ſo that this ſhall make an Englyſhe preſte, be he neuer ſuche a dolt or vnlearnid in the knouledge of the ſcripture as we haue very manye, and without theſe romiſſhe reliques not Paule hym ſelfe ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be admittid (as one of them dyd blaſpheme &amp; the reſt of them in effecte do affirme) well agaynſte ſuche popiſhe chaffer and popery, hathe byne longe agone foughten withe all, when the gret captaines of that religion ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd, and yet God gaue the victory. Therfor let vs not fear now, although it doth begine to ſture agayn, for ther is no craft, conuinge, counſell, wyſdom, or policy againſt the Lord. We haue Chriſt &amp; hys Apoſtells &amp; the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes euer ſtryuing agaynſt the Ipocrites
<pb facs="tcp:177160:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> of their time on our ſyde: a ſtrau for popiſhe polici we haue the worde of God to warant vs, to rote out al monuments of ſuperſticion and Idolatry, &amp; are charged to abhor them, to accompt them, accurſed, and to defy them, and to deteſt them as menſtreous clowtes, they haue not the worde of God for them. And what wyſdom is in them, ſayth god by his Prophet Ieremi, they talke of obedience &amp; concorde, but ther is no obedience againſt the Lorde, no nor concorde to be deſired, but wher gods glory and verite is preſerued, Els better to haue al the worlde in hurly burleis, and heauen &amp; earth to ſhake, then one ioyte of gods glory ſhulde decaie. So far forth as in vs leithe, we haue theyr owne lawes and proclamacious, to rote out all monuments of ſuperſticion and Idolatrye, &amp; theyr oune wordes are contrarye to theyr doinges. Yt ſhulde apere that they repent their reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion proclamid, as did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſralites, they buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de agayn that which ons they haue diſtroied and this is done openlye that all the worlde may wonder, and behold: but what is done ſecretlye, god wyll one daye haue it declarid openly, ye they make the name of god &amp; this doctrine that we profeſſe to be euell ſpoken of alredy. By many of theyr doinges, theyr iudgement haſteth that for ſuch cauſes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Gods true preachers. Wherfor let vs
<pb facs="tcp:177160:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> not feare theyr threteninges, ther can none perſecute the godly for this cauſe &amp; traſſhe. but ether ſuch as are nether hote nor colde and then they ſhalbe vomyted out vnleſſe their zeale encreaſe, or ſuch as haue no God before their eies, whoſe god is their bellie, or els open papiſts, whom god hathe geuen vp to a reprobate ſenſe, wherfore we muſt thus take it, that they ar gods rodds for oure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, becauſe we haue not ben more zelous in Gods cauſe, nether carefull to ſeke his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, that wolfe Wyncheſter &amp; blodie bucher Bonar fought once againſt many godli men for the grounde of this gere, and thei had all the power of the Realme ſeruinge theyr lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, but beholde how the Lorde in ſhort time ouerthrew them al, to giue vs coradge to go forwarde, the Lord forgeue vs, we ar to ſlac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and neglygent in heauenly thynges, this monſter Bonar remainithe and is fed as pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſay, for their ſakes, &amp; it muſt be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyd, it is for ſome purpos, althoughe he be a traytor and an enemi to the crowne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, and bothe to God and man, whiche brunnid godes holy teſtament, murderid his ſaintes and his ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. But what the Lord requyrith to be done wythe falſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes it is manyfeſt: we haue bothe the lawe of god &amp; man for vs, But we ar anſwerid nay, you your ſealues ſhalbe compellid to turne
<pb facs="tcp:177160:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> your coates and cappes, and get you into his leueris, and to be lyke him in your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. O Elyas that thou lyuedſte, or that thy ſpyrit weare amongſt vs, thou woldeſt ſay with the Prophet Sophoni, that God will vyſit the werears of this Idolatours garmentes or ſtrange aparell, thou woldeſt ſay, that thinges dedicatid once to idolatry, is not indifferent, thou woldeſt ſay reuerence to the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is wrought by doctrine and diſcipline, and not by popiſſhe &amp; Idolatours garments, thou woldeſt ſaye, what decency can ther be gaynyd to the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, by that which hath byn deuiſyd &amp; vſyd to deface it, if the golde ordeinyd by god for the reuerence and decenci of the Iewes temple, is not to be admittyd to beutify the churche of Chriſte, much leſſe copes brought in by papiſtes the enemyes of god, and alwayes continwyd in their ſeruice as orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of their religion in no wyſe ought of vs Chriſtians to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynid. But the papiſtes triumphe and glori in their aſſembles, that the hote goſpelars ſhalbe driuen to their doltiſhe attires, for the Lords ſake let vs neuer giue them any cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of Ioye, thoughe we ſhoulde dye for yt: Moyſes wold not yelde on hoofe of a beſte in gods buſines, he wolde not leue the lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe vnmade nor make a button or a claſpe more or leſſe. Eleaſar will not decemble by
<pb facs="tcp:177160:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> eatynge of vnlawfull meates the faythfull Iſralites wolde not receyue ſo muche as an yui buſhe. Contrariwyſe Orygen caryinge a braunche and profeſſynge, that he bare it for Chriſt at the firſt. But was afterwarde compellid to open Idolatry, ſo curſid a thing it is to geue any place to the wicked: all the papiſtes that ſaye, they worſhip Chriſt in the croſſe, and God in the ſacrament, do ſtill vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe wordes continew ſtill in their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latri, beware of deceitfull wordes, that couer wickid purpoſes, to drawe vs from Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſymplicite. Let vs ſtand conſtantly agaynſte all abuſes, and repent for our former cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in religion, and our ſynnes, and call for healpe from aboue, for the hand of the Lorde is not ſhortenid: we ar aſſured that we ſeke Gods glory, and our aduerſaries may ſee, yf they can ſe any thinge, that this thinge that they ſeke is not for gods glory, ſeing the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes the enemyes of God, doe ſo deſyre yt and glory in yt. And reioyſe, that we, whom they moſt hate, cannot be ſafe but vnder their garments: we ar aſſurid that we ſeke godes glory in folowinge Chriſt his Apoſteles and Prophets. who euer diſpiſed theſe phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call outward faces and viſures, Chriſte fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dethe fault withe the garmentes of the pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeis. Paule counteth all his phariſaicall,
<pb facs="tcp:177160:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhew to be donge. Zachari ſaithe, that the falſe Prophet ſhalbe aſhamed of his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, and forſake his garments wherin he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuid. &amp; ſhal the true Prophetes be fayne to crepe into their coules? for by the ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torite may be comaundid any peace of pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſo that it be namyd policie. Ezechias and Ioſias knew no ſuche aucthoritie, but they ſay: It is for policie, For it plainly apearithe that ther is leſſe care for religion, then for policie. But beware that the example of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboham be not folowed, that made ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke preſtes for policie as wolde do as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundid them. Achaz of policie brought the faſhion of an alter into Ieruſalem, as he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we at Damaſcus, where he had ouercome the Idolatours and their Idolls, but curſed was his policie, and ſo ar all they that wil retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne any thinge of their Idolatrie. Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſors Idoll was for vnitye and policie, but without the warraunt of gods worde, ther is neyther good vnitye nor police. The godlie father Bucer callithe the tenthes and the firſt fruites ſacriledge and roberie, they be kept ſtil for policie. Croſſe and candelſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes at ſuperſticious, though they be kepte. I wot not for what policie the adoration of the Sacrament in the countres, where they knocke and knele to a wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r cake is a popi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:177160:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> policie. That wemen baptiſe, that plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, tot quots impropriacions, non reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, deſpenſacions, ſuſpenſions, excomunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; abſolucions, for money ar grauntyd, yt is evell, like as are many other inormites borowed from Rome, which remayne in the name of policie. All theſe thinges were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horryd as popiſhe ſuperſticions, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, amonge our goſpellers both biſhops &amp; others, when they were vnder gods roddes in pouerte. But how thei now haue learnid courtely deuinite, to grounde all apon poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie? Humble them agayne o Lorde, that they do not forget the, and thy great kindnes and mercie ſhewid apon them, and ſture vp their hartes and myndes, that they may be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ouer thy pore flocke. O Chriſte, whom thou haſt dearly bought, by this theyr poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ar blindid, &amp; carithe for no more, but that thei may haue this ſuperſticious ſhew which is ſo ſtifely maintained. Let him mumble as he liſte, yf he be thus apparelid, al his ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is well ynough, otherwyſe yt is nothing worthe. Thus cauſe you them to periſhe by your polices, for whome Chriſt hathe dyed. further more, yf poperi be ſuperſtitious and idolatrous, evel and wicked, as yet therwas neuer a worſe thinge in the worlde, then ar we commaunded to abſteine from all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177160:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> therof, and from all the ſhewe therof <hi>ab omni ſpecie mali,</hi> that is, from all ſhewe of wickidnes. Theſe garments were the ſhewe of their blaſphemous preiſthod, herein they dyd ſinge and ſaye their ſuperſticious idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſeruice, they dyd ſence their Idolls and healpe forwarde theyr Idolatrous maſſes, what policie can it be then to weare this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. But a ſuperſticious wickid and popiſhe policie, they doe it for policie, they ſaye, that their prieſtes may be knowen and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of men. Dyd not the Phariſies vſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me policie, to doe all their workes and make all their garmentes bothe Philacteris vpon their headdes, and their wide and ſyde robes and borders, that they might be more expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and notorious to the people? but their woo is thretenid aboue al other ſinners. To ſuche ypocrites, as beinge voyde of all true holynes, delite in all outward ſhewes, theyr curſe is moſt inculcate, their polyci is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preiſtes ſhall weare white in the churches to ſignify their vertue, their purenes, and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lines. and when they go fourth of the church they muſt weare blacke gownes and blacke hornes, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary polycies, and for dyuers ſignificacions, Our maſter Chriſtes polycie was expreſſyd in one worde, fede, fede, fede. and the Prophetes before, and the Apoſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:177160:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> afterwarde, yf Chriſte be the wyſdome of the father, the true miniſters ſhalbe well inough knowen, by that one marke which he geueth: and yf that he haue not that mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke better vnknowen then knowen, both for him ſelfe and others, therfore lett them not ſaye for ſhame, that they ſeeke gods glorie, Chriſtes wil, or the edification of his church, by their polycie. Whyles they threte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſtope the ſpredinge of gods worde and fedinge of Chriſtes flocke, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandyd by writing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the moſt faithful laborers in the planting of the goſpell, becauſe thei will not weare the rages of popery, to expulſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt valiant ſoldiars agaynſt the Romiſhe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, the moſt earneſt ouerthrowars of the kyngdom of ſatan, which ſtandith in ſin and blindnes. O beware you, that wilbe Lordes ouer the flockes, that you be not ſore puny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for your pryde, towardes your brethren, and your cowardlines in gods cauſe, that for Princes pleaſures and pompoſe liuinges, do turne poperi into policie, and to become our perſecutors vnder the cloke of policie: it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re better to loſe your liuings, then to diſple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſe god in perſecutinge of youre brethren, &amp; hinder the courſe of the worde. But as oure deutie is, we wyll praye for you, and for all our brethren in the miniſteri, that god of his
<pb facs="tcp:177160:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> grace would graunte vs more zeale for his glorie, than any of vs hathe had heretofore, more deſire to edifie, Chriſtes people in pure ſimplicite, to preſent them a chaſt virgin vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt then hitherto hathe apeared, that when the he deſhepherde ſhall cal to accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, we be not aſhamyd. But beinge founde perfecte in all good workes, may receiue the crowne prepared, as for you deare brethren whome God hath callyd into the brunte of the batell, The Lorde kepe ye conſtant, that ye yelde nether to tolleracion, nether to anye other ſubtelte perſuaſions of diſpenſacions, or lycences which were to fortifie their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhe practiſes. but as you fyght the Lords fyght, be valiant. God will not leue you, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſake you, as you ſeke gods glorye, god wyll glorifye you, and as by you Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes church is edifyed, comfortid and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid in Chriſtian ſimplycite, ſo ſhall you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue comfort by Chriſte your heede captai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, when you ſhalbe callyd to geue acomptes of your ſtewardſhippes, and to be rewardyd for your fidelite, the matter is not ſo ſmalle as the worlde do take yt, yt wyll appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all be endyd, what an harde thinge it is, to cut of the rages of the Hidra of Rome, it is beutifull, but poyſonful, ther is no daling with ſuch a mounſter, beware of lokyng bac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:177160:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> to Sodome or delyght anye witte in the garments of Babilone, neyther once touche the poyſonid cupe, though yt be of golde or gliteringe. Let vs repent of our former ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnfaynidlye, and then ſhall we abhor and ſtamp vnder our fette theſe rages, that were apoyntid to ſuperſticion and idolatry, Let vs hate the blaſphemous preaſthode, ſo iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Chriſtes preiſthode, that euery pache and token of it be in execration, deteſtation, and accurſed, and take no parte of yt vpon our heddes nor backes, leaſt we be accurſed as it is. Let vs not make the heritage of god as a byrde of many colours, holdinge of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers religions, Let vs not mixte the Iewes with the gentills, let vs not in no wiſe mixt this our religion with any thinge of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, let vs not confyrme the blinde in their blindnes, neyther the weacke in their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion. But rather let vs take awaye, if we can, the names, memories, and all monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of poperye and that Antichriſtes prieſthood. Let vs open our wyndous with Daniel, and profeſſe what we ar: their cruelte ſhalbe our glorie. Let vs followe Paull, that knew that the truthe goſpel cold not be retainyd, if any Iewiſhe cerimonies were mayntainyd. Lett vs rather neuer weare anye garment, then we ſhould weare thoſe, wherby our brethren
<pb facs="tcp:177160:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhulde be weakened, offendyd or boldenyd to take parte with the idolatours, &amp; ſo through our hautines in knouledge, oure weake bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren periſhe, for whom Chriſt died. Behold and marke well, how they falle backwarde that yelde in anye iote, and ſe how they are edifyed, and increaſe in godlines, which holde that ryght waye that you goe in, the which the Lorde increaſe you, &amp; vs all, and ſtrenthen vs with his holy ſpyrit, that we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinewe to oure lyues ende, al wayes both by our thoughtes, wordes, and workes, to avaunce his glorye and honor dayly more and more, now and for euer. </p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>¶ Grace and peace with all maner ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual feling and liuing worthi of the kindnes of Chriſt, be with all that thriſt the will of God.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>TO my faythfull and deare brethren in Chriſt Ieſu,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>as in comen daungers of fier, or ſuche lyke, welbelouyd, they that be fare of, com to ſocoure thoſe that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue nede, ſo I beinge out of iepordie and far of,<note place="margin">tru Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian loue.</note> can not but of deuty wyſhe well to thoſe that be touchyd about the popiſhe apparell in thys libertye of Gods truthe, whyche is tought plainely without offencis, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſt miſterys of our religion and ſaluacion, yt is much to be marvayled, that this ſmall controuerſye of aparell ſhould be ſo heuely taken. But this is the mallis of ſatan,<note place="margin">the practiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kid.</note> that wher he can not ouerthrow the greatiſt mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, he will cauſe great troubels in trifels. Peter and Paule agreyde in the greatyſte articles of our ſaluacion, and yet they diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd ſo about meattes, that Paule withſtode and rebuckid hym openly.<note place="margin">the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites of the godly.</note> Paule and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas fell at ſuche bytter contencion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Marke ſhuld go with them or no, that they partyd companyes, and eyther of them went ſondry waies. God defend vs from the lyke.<note place="margin">the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the godly</note> Paule circumciſyd Timothe when ther
<pb facs="tcp:177160:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> was hope to wine the Iewes: but when they wold haue it of neceſſite, he would not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe Titus, therfore compellinge would not be vſyd in thinges of liberte, yt is a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table caſe, that among them that are civil &amp; full of knouledge, that yt ſhuld come thus to paſſe. Conſyder dearly belouyd, I beſech you, how that all countres, whiche haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formid religion, haue caſt away the popiſhe aparell with the pope: and yet we that wyll be taken for the beſt goſpelars, are contentid to kepe it as an holie religion. Marke well alſo how many godly and learnid miniſters ther be here in all countres, that be ſo zelous not onlie to forſake the wickyd doctrine of poperie, ready to leue the minyſtry, &amp; to loſe lyuinges, rather then to be lyke the popiſhe teachers of ſuperſticious order in aparell or behaviour. This realme hath ſuch ſkacite of teachers, that yf ſo many worthye men and learnid ſhuld be caſt out of the miniſtrie for ſuche ſmall matters, many placis ſhulde be deſtitude of preachers, &amp; yt wold geue an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable offence to all the fauourars of gods truthe here, and in other countres, alſo ſhall we make ſo much and ſo precious of the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes rages, that other reformyd places, exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me as vyle &amp; filthye, God forbid. S. Paule byddith wemen vſe ſuche aparell as beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mith
<pb facs="tcp:177160:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> them that profes true godlines, which rule is muche more to be obſeruid of men, &amp; eſpeciallye of preachers. But yf we forſake popery as wickid, ſhall we ſay that their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell becommith ſaintes, and profeſſars of tru holines. Saint Paule bydith vs refraine from al outward ſhew of evell, but ſurely in kepinge of this popiſhe aparell, we forbear not an outwarde ſhew of much evell, yf po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery be iudgid evell, as greter wickidnes can not be, as we wolde haue a diuers ſhewe of aparel to be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the comon people, ſo is yt neceſſary in aparell, to haue a ſhew, howe a proteſtante is to be knowen from a papiſte. Yt hathe pleaſyd God to call vs to preache his heuenly worde to that hye office, God geue you grace and vs all to ſeke hys honor &amp; glorie yf we ſo do with a pure hart and mynde, he hath promyſed, He that hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith me, I will glorify him, and he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnith me, I wyll contemne him. Let ther be no curtiſye made to healpe gods people now they be in danger. Call to your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce Quene Eaſter, ſhe be gaue to make curtiſy to ſpeke in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cauſe, but Mardocheus ſayd vnto her: Yf thou now hold thy peace, God ſhall delyuer by an other meane, &amp; yet thou &amp; thy fathers houſe ſhall peryſhe. You that can and may do good, do it whyle tyme
<pb facs="tcp:177160:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> is offerid, the tyme will come when it wylbe to late: yet god wyll comfort his by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane: It ys a perilous thinge, not to healpe in the tyme of neade, &amp; not to ſuffer religion to goe forward in all ſyncerite, and to further gods cauſe when ye maye, when Terenti a good Chriſtian captaine returnid with great triumphe &amp; victory, the Emperor Valerius bade him are what he wold, and he ſhuld haue it for his good ſeruice: he hauing God before his eyes, deſyrd nether ryches, nether honor, but thoſe which had aduente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their liues for true religion, might haue a church alowid them, to ſerue their god pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely in, &amp; ſeueral from the Arrians. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour beyng angrie with his requeſt, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd his ſupplicacion in pecis, and bade him axe ſom other thing. but he gathered vp the pecis of his, paper and ſayd: I haue receuid my rewarde, I wyll axe nothinge els, God encrece about Princes the ſmall nomber of ſuche zelous ſuters &amp; promoters of religion, and then no doubt gods glorye ſhall floriſhe when we ſeke his dewe honor, and not oure owne profyte. But to avoide contencion &amp; ſciſme Auſten gevith good counſel to godly and quiet men, that they mercifully correcte that whiche they can, &amp; that which they can not, paciently beare, grone and morne, with
<pb facs="tcp:177160:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> loue, vntil god ether correct or amend them. But how this Chriſtian loue ſhuld be kept in this church, when ſo manye godlie for ſo ſmall thinges ſhalbe thruſte out, &amp; alſo how many already is from the miniſtery &amp; theyr lyuinges, yt paſſyth manye good and godlie wittes to conceyue. S. Pauls rule in ſuche thinges, ſayth: All thinges to me is lawfull, but all thinges is not expedient: all thinges to me is lawfull, but all thinges edefye not. Therfor in this caſe we muſt not ſo ſuttelly diſpute, what Chriſtian liberte will ſuffer vs to do, but what is metiſt and moſt edefying for Chriſtian charite, &amp; promoting Chriſtian and pure religion. But ſurely how popiſhe aparell ſhuld edefie, or ſet forwarde the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt Ieſus, it can not be ſeen of the multitude, nay, it is to much fealt how gred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it reioyſith the aduerſaries of the truth, when they ſee what we borowe of them, &amp; contend for the ſame as thinges neceſſarie. marke well the byſſhopes wearing of their whyte rochets, what grounde they fyrſte had, and from whence they receyuid it. Ther was a certayne man, namid Siſinius an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riticke biſhop of the Novacions, and he firſt begane yt. all thoſe other popiſh traſhe hath the lyke foundacions, but they haue to long contineuyd &amp; pleaſyd poperie, which is beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly
<pb facs="tcp:177160:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> patchid vp of al ſortes of cerimones, &amp; that they coulde neuer be routyd out ſence, no not from manie profeſſors of the goſpel. Wherfore you that ſe others that is come to a better perfection, grudge not at yt, but be thankfull to God, though thynges may be borne wythe for a tyme for Chriſtian ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertes ſake, in hope to winne the weake. yet when lyberte is turnyd into neceſſite, yt ys evell, &amp; no lenger lyberte: and that, that was for wynning the weake ſufferid for a tyme, is become the confyrminge of the frowarde in their obſtinacie. Paul vſyd circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion for a tyme as of lyberte, but when it was vrgyd of neceſſite, he wold not bende vnto it. That famous father Maſter Bucer, when he was aryd why he wolde not weare a ſquare cape, made aunſwere, becauſe hys heade was not foure ſquare. wherin ſurelye he notyd well the comlynes of aparell to be, when yt was faſſionyd lyke the body, &amp; a gret folly when a ſquare cape was ſet on a rounde heade.</p>
                  <p>God be mercyfull vnto vs, and graunte vs vprightly to ſeke hys honore wyth all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtnes &amp; ſimplicite. The Lorde comfort his afflictid church, &amp; graunte that in this oulde age of the worlde, we may ſerue the Lord of hoſtes in ſynglenes of hart, and laboure to rote out all ſtomblinge blockes in religion,
<pb facs="tcp:177160:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> that Chriſtes glorie maye nakydly ſhyne of yt ſealue, without all tradicions or inuenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, as in the begynninge when yt was pureſt, and all ſuch deuyſes vnknowen, but inuentid of late to bleare the eyes of the ignorant, with outwarde ſhewe of holines. God graunt that we may geue all honor to whom al honore is deue, both inwardly and outwardly, to ſerve hym vnfaynedlye al the dayes of oure lyfe. Fare well deare brethren in the Lorde Ieſu, who euer kepe vs in hys fayth, feare, and loue, for euer. </p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:40"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:41"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177160:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
